And so it's my pleasure today
to welcome Charles from Modal.
So Charles builds and teaches
people to build AI applications.
And after publishing research
in psychopharmacology?
Psychopharmacology, yeah.
--and neurobiology,
he got his PhD
at the University of
California at Berkeley.
Don't hold it against me--
for dissertation work on
neural network optimization.
And he has taught thousands the
entire stack of AI application
development, from
linear algebra,
and GPU arcana to building
defensible businesses--
through work at
weights and biases,
full stack deep
learning, and model.
So without further ado,
I'll hand it off to Charles.
Great.
Thanks for the
introduction, Steven.
[APPLAUSE]
OK.
So what I wanted
to talk about today
is serving the
models that you've
learned about in previous
talks in this course.
And I took a look at what
some of the other speakers
talked about, like
the ultrascale.
The ultrascale talk,
the state space models
talk, and there's a lot
of focus on capabilities
and on the production
of these models.
And that's super important.
That's where things start.
But where they end up
is being used by people.
And so that's what
I've been working
on a lot in the last
couple of years.
And so I want to share
some lessons about this.
I think maybe if you are
dead set on training,
then you will maybe
learn some things
about the consequences of your
choices in training models.
Maybe I can convince you that
inference is interesting too.
So that's a bit of a spoiler
for my why inference.
So Sean Wang recently
tweeted that everyone
in AI infrastructure is
finally getting filthy rich.
And he clarified, not sexy AI
research, just boring infra.
And this was right
after our company
announced our raise, along
with a couple of others.
So I think I know what
he's talking about here.
So also somebody who posted
a thing about auto research.
And it was a paper about
using auto research
on making inference faster.
And he was like,
you can also use
auto research for boring
things, like inference.
So I wanted to go through this
because I feel like, yeah, it's
inference has a bit of--
yeah, it's the younger
brother of training.
Yeah.
So one just big reason
to care about this--
training is cool, but from
the perspective of a business,
it's a cost center,
not a revenue center.
You put money in, and
a model comes out.
And then there's not actually a
good way to turn model weights
into money directly.
It's kind of software, where
it's pretty hard to sell,
like a CD with software on it.
But so you have to
turn it into something.
Create a system around it.
And that's how you're
actually able to make
the revenue that allows you
to keep making the models.
And yeah, even if
you're just raising
venture capital from people
who just keep signing checks--
they want to see
revenue along the way.
And so this is pretty.
This makes it pretty important.
It also means it's just like
attracts a lot of resources
over time, and it's
useful as an engineer
to have more resources
to tackle the problems.
Training it's also--
it's pretty important,
but it's done by only a
few organizations right
now, especially pre-training.
It's how there's only a few
organizations that fab chips,
and most people
build on top of that.
Or even ones like NVIDIA
opted for the CPUs--
they're compiling intellectual
property components
from other people.
Inference is, on the
other hand, everywhere.
There are many people
running inference and more
I would say all the time.
Also just even to do
training nowadays,
you want to generate
outputs from the model,
have them interact
with the world,
and then feed that back
into the weights usually
with reinforcement learning.
This is important part of
the training stack now.
Maybe more flops
than the pre-train.
I don't know if people that yet.
And this requires you to
do efficient inference.
So even the training
heads, I think,
have to care a lot
about these things now.
Reason I care about it a
lot or I enjoy it a lot--
inference right
now especially is
like straddling the whole stack.
You have to think
about applications.
What's this being used for?
You have to think about
linear algebra or cute
template algebras,
layout algebras.
And you need to think
about electrons, and heat,
and cooling.
And so that's a pretty fun place
to play as a truly full stack
engineer.
And then finally,
there's a big wave
of inference demand oncoming--
both for the models put out by
the proprietary providers then
just all over the place.
And that's a big
opportunity for engineers
to service that demand
efficiently for people.
And then wireless
[INAUDIBLE] about this.
I've been working on inference
at Modal for about the last two
years-- previously on
how to train and deploy
models at full stack deep
learning and then on training
before that.
So I've gone through
this whole stack.
Been focused recently internally
at modern GPU stuff, metrics,
profiling, performance,
where the rubber hits
the road with inference.
And I've both been running my
own [INAUDIBLE] little language
servers for my own projects and
then also more seriously working
with a bunch of
the leading teams,
which you'll see on this
slide that are deploying
and optimizing inference
at the scale of hundreds
or thousands of GPUs.
And unlike some of the
other people in this field,
I have no interest in hiding
this knowledge from people.
I want them to all know
about it and do it.
I want there to be more
inference in the world.
So all right-- let's
go through the stack.
What does it take
to serve inference,
and what are the most important
things and tools to know about?
We only have about an hour
here, so I'm not going
to be able to go into detail.
This is like a slap bang
world tour at high speed.
So we'll have
questions afterwards,
and I'll be at the
event after that.
I'm happy to go in more
detail about these things,
but I just want to make sure to
cover a survey of everything.
So the rough outline
here is that we're
going to cover applications.
What are people trying to do?
And quickly break that
down into the things
that you want to think about
as the engineer servicing
those applications.
What are the workloads,
and what are the objectives
of the service that services
those workloads on behalf
of those applications?
Then there's the components
that go into servicing
that workload-- the models
that produce the inferences
and the engines that orchestrate
the production of inferences.
Those things need
to run on hardware.
This is more
important than it has
been in many other eras of
the development of software
applications, so we'll
spend some time on that.
That has implications for how
these things are deployed.
For now, this is substantially
like cloud and data center
deployment, so we'll
talk a lot about that.
Once you have these
things deployed,
you need to debug them.
You need to set up
observability, the ability
to debug and fix, resolve faults
and failures from just logs.
With that basic
stuff in place, you
can do performance
optimization--
ensure that you are
hitting your SLOs
or decreasing your
costs over time.
And then we'll end with just a
few thoughts on what I believe
is next in this field
because I'm mostly
going to talk about what's
happening right now.
OK.
Applications-- let's start with
just a quick breakdown of LLM
application archetypes.
This is a very
infra-brained approach
because it's mostly about
trying to figure out
what are the
engineering constraints
that I have to service these.
So I break it down
into three kind
of things like chatbot plus,
background agent, and data
processor.
Chatbot plus is the one most
people are familiar with.
It is basically two
of the killer apps
that we've seen so far
for language models.
ChatGPT and Claude code
fit in this archetype.
There is a human
on the other end.
They have human reaction
time, human latency tolerances
and interests.
And I say chatbot plus
because it's not just yapping.
It's also that this thing
uses its text outputs
to interact with other computer
systems on behalf of the user.
So the other
application that does
a lot of interacting
directly with other computer
systems on the behalf of
users is background agents.
So this is something like the
dev encoding agent Resolve's SRE
agent, Ramps Inspect coding
agent, or Open Inspect,
or OpenClaw.
These are all
systems where there
is a human relatively tight.
They probably produce
many of the tokens
in the prompt, the
most important tokens
in the prompt
themselves directly,
but they aren't necessarily
waiting for the result.
They're in a meeting.
Somebody asked them to
implement a feature,
and they've tagged Devin
or Inspector or whatever
to implement the feature
for them and open a PR.
So you don't have interactive
human latency constraints.
You just have some
latency constraint
on the order of many seconds,
many minutes, many hours.
And then finally, data
processors-- the prototypes here
are something like the
reducto processing platform.
They're the ones who indexed the
emails of International Criminal
Jeffrey Epstein for the jail
project, which turned it
into an email interface.
This is the situation
where what you want to do
is you want to process
maybe some PDFs
and documents, some
unstructured data
and extract structure
from it-- common use case.
And here, the
downstream consumer
is probably like a
storage computer system
that will be queried later.
So it's going into file system.
It's going into a database--
something like that.
So high volume, higher
latency tolerance, but often,
as with many databases
and storage systems,
very bursty gaps between
periods of sparse writes
and very intense writes.
OK.
So these are the archetypes that
you keep in mind as we're going.
I'll refer back to
them as we're thinking
about optimization techniques.
Yeah.
So that is maybe
how the people who
are developing products or
your application engineers
are going to be
thinking about problems.
As somebody developing
an inference system,
you're going to be thinking
at a lower level than them.
And the hand-off point
is like a definition
of a workload of
what work is going
to be submitted to a system and
what constraints the application
places on how that
workload is serviced.
So you'll hear service
level agreements--
SLAs or service
level objectives,
SLOs, to describe the
constraints or expectations
in terms of failure rates,
performance like speed,
and cost as well.
And this is the handoff point
between the engineer of a system
and the other
stakeholders in a system.
So we were working with a
lot of customers, who wanted
to build LLM inference systems.
And we would ask them-- they
wanted our help, our expertise,
and getting information about
the workload out of them
was challenging.
So I developed this thing that's
available in our LLM engineers
Almanac.
That's a little
Madlibs that asks
you to define your workload.
So click each one
of these things
and select like
which model you want
to serve, what your
constraints on performance are,
and both in terms of
latency in the top right,
and in terms of throughput
on the bottom left.
So you can check that out.
The models in it are
a little out of date,
but stay tuned for
a major update soon.
That should keep
it much fresher.
So really what I just
want to point out here
is like this specific
selection of ways
to define what the workload
is that you want to run.
Because this clarified
and shortened
a lot of otherwise
difficult conversations.
So the key thing here is
to define these workloads
via a bunch of metrics.
So you have queries
per second, QPS.
This one is under
control of users.
It's often tricky to forecast.
You make something you
don't whether people
are going to want it or use
it, and there's quite a bit
of variability or seasonality.
People often don't think about
that variability or seasonality.
But if you can try and
figure that out early.
That's important because that
changes how difficult it is.
The higher the ratio
between your average traffic
and your peak traffic,
the more difficult
it is to serve a system.
So that's something
to get ahead of early.
Within those queries--
those queries usually
that might be user
queries, or it
might be queries generated
by the model via tool calls.
What you want to find
out about those queries
is how many tokens you can
expect in those queries--
how many tokens in the
inputs during profile phases,
and how many tokens in the
output in DECOD phases.
So this one's really annoying
because it's not only
under control of the users.
It's also under
control of the model
because the model decides when
to emit the end of text token.
And so your output
lengths are actually not
necessarily deterministic.
Or you can try and make them
deterministic in some settings,
but even then, they
may be literally
deterministic on the same
inputs and same seed,
but they're very hard to reason
about because they're coming out
of the statistical model.
So that's bad news.
It's a little bit
different-- it's maybe
similar to a database in that
when the data in the database
changes, query
performance changes.
And so you just have to
be empirical about it
in many cases.
So you can estimate this.
This is maybe a
little bit easier
than estimating how many
queries there are going to be,
because that depends
on whether you're
on the front page of Hacker News
or tweeted out by an influencer
or whatever.
That determines your
queries per second.
Prefix reuse-- this
is another one.
How often when a sequence of
tokens comes in from a user
is it some tokens that
you've seen before?
This is really
important because you
can cache your previous
computations and store them.
People get very elaborate
with these approaches.
This is pretty powerful,
especially in situations
with lower interactivity,
because you can just
delay, turn, what would
be GPU computation
into loads from storage.
And that's really
nice for your costs
at often at a cost to latency.
So I mostly think of it as
something that I use when--
aggressive kV caching
in a case where
I have users with a
greater latency tolerance.
This is mostly under
control of the users,
but given that users write short
prompts of dozens of tokens
and models observe prompts
with thousands of tokens,
this is in fact under
the control of something.
Maybe a harness or
other software system
that you may have
some control over.
And so then you can be
smart or dumb about it,
and you can also
ban people using
unhinged lobster-themed
software from your endpoints
if it busts your cache.
Yeah.
So then I've alluded to latency
budgets a couple of times.
There's basically two that
matter-- the time to first token
and the time per output
token or inter-token latency.
So time to first token.
How long does it take to get the
first token or first byte back
to the user?
And then how long does it take
to produce each sequential token
after that?
Time to last token also
matters, but because it
depends on the output length
and very, very directly, very
painfully and obviously
depends on that output length,
it's often easier to reason
about time per output token
and output lengths separately.
And then when you need to
think about time to last token,
you combine them together.
And then once you
start doing tool calls,
all hell breaks loose.
And you have to go back to being
pretty empirical with live data.
So latency budget is going to
be defined by your application.
It's one of the main things that
separated the three application
classes we discussed
on the previous slide.
And maybe one important
thing about this
is with time per output token
and input token latency,
you really want to
be thinking per user.
What is the experience
of an individual user
or an individual
request in this system?
In every case, except the bulk
data processing because that
is what--
these are defined
by the application.
They're defined by
the user experience.
And so that's what you
need to care about,
not the machine experience.
Yeah.
One last tip about
this is you really
want to reason about
this per replica.
So you have a whole
system-- particular QPS.
QPS is something people
will say like, oh, I
think I'm going to have a
thousand concurrent users,
and they'll send a query
every couple of seconds,
and then they'll reason
their way to total QPS.
That is very helpful to know.
That gives you the
aggregate demand,
but you're going
to probably end up
serving this with multiple
replicas, multiple machines
running an inference engine.
And so you need to be able to--
and that's the amount--
there's a certain
number of queries you
could fit in a single replica.
And then like hitting
these latency budgets,
and then you can--
and also your prefix reuse.
And then so that sets
the number of queries
you can handle per replica.
And then you add replicas, until
you can satisfy the total load.
So this is different
than a database,
where you try to avoid
having multiple replicas,
until your IPO--
and because inference is
independent across the engines.
Each of them can operate
essentially independently apart
from the prefix caching.
So for our three
archetypes, the figure
of merit that you care about
in each workload is different.
So for chatbot plus, you
care about interactivity,
which is tokens per
second per user--
mostly output tokens
per second per user.
For a background agent, you
care about time to last token
because that's when you produce
the result that the human is
waiting on-- the PR, the design
doc, the generated image.
With data processors,
you care mostly
about how quickly you can
chunk through stuff, so
like mega tokens per dollar.
Great.
And that comes from your
throughput in tokens
per second aggregate,
appropriately mixed
between input and output.
So I said you want to reason
about at the level of one
replica then scale up.
So how do you
benchmark one replica?
Quick and easy recipe.
First, figure out
your minimum latency.
What's the fastest you could
run this thing if every user got
their own replica?
So run n queries one
at a time, and then
record one over the mean
latency max throughput.
Dump n queries at once, and then
record n over the total latency.
So this is if all
your requests hit
the replica at the
same time, wait,
see how quickly it can
chunk through them.
Expose the maximum
amount of parallelism
to the engine and the hardware.
So that will give you a minimum
throughput and minimum latency
and maximum throughput with
a generally higher latency.
And then you can measure the
behavior of replicas in between
want to sweep over
in between rates.
So this badly needs a diagram.
So the idea is here
I send one query.
Wait for it to finish,
then send another query,
then wait for it to finish,
then send another query.
And that gives me the shortest
latency I've ever observed.
And then with max throughput,
hit it with everything at once.
Wait for it to finish.
So notice how this one is
shorter, the max throughput,
because it'll generally
finish all the requests faster
if you give them all at once,
but any given request takes
longer.
So yeah, if you're
a systems of a--
signals.
And W type engineer think of
this as an impulse response
that you're measuring
in the system.
Cool.
So to develop an
intuition for metrics,
put out this cute little tool.
Because you want to see
what these things look
like to decide, oh, is
this a good experience.
Let me zoom out a little bit.
So this one is really fast.
This is some optimizations
that I like measured those.
Put them into this
little simulator.
And this is without
those optimizations.
And just to give you a sense
for why we care about things
like P95 or P99
latency, like, let's
keep the P50 latency
on the left the same
and then boost those tails.
So you measure something
like P95 and P99.
You think, oh, only one
out of every 20 or one
out of every 100 users
experiences this.
How big of a deal could it be?
But you're usually
measuring these things
at the scale of a
single sequence.
You're looking at P95 completion
of a sequence, P95 production
of a token in this case.
And so you can see even though
the median token comes out
in a millisecond, in this case,
you see all this stuttering.
And if you are probably
familiar with this
if you've used many of
the inference providers,
because there are frequently
these long tails that
are hard to control.
So I find this tool
useful for when
I want to show people the
improvements without having
to record traces, which
can be difficult. Cool.
So that's on the LLM
engineer's Almanac as well.
All right.
So that's workloads and SLOs.
Again, as I said earlier just
ripping through this stuff,
so we have time for
questions about the things
people are most
interested in at the end.
All right.
So models and engines.
So in my opinion models are
also part of the workload.
You want to-- for
inference engineering,
you want the
application developer
to decide running like
the transformers version
of the model in a
Jupyter Notebook
what model quality is necessary
to service the application.
So it fits under the workloads,
but the model that you're using
is one of the most important
decisions that is made.
What I've observed is that
there are two basic families
of constraints that lead
to very different model
options and model choices.
So I call them efficiency
bound and capability bound.
Efficiency bound means that
intelligence is satisfactory.
It's not that hard for
the trainers of models
to produce a model that
can solve this task.
And once that happens, cost
becomes the primary driver.
And in this domain, open models
have generally dominated.
The proprietary providers are
not going after these workloads.
What they're going after
instead are these capability
bound workloads, where the
highest intelligence that
currently exists is not enough.
And to some extent, it
may never be enough.
One analogy I give here is
like efficiency bound is
like refresh rates on monitors.
Once you hit like 60
Hertz, it's pretty good.
You hit a hundred
Hertz, it's amazing.
Very few people want
a thousand Hertz.
But RAM on the other hand,
we're at 64 gigabytes
in people's laptops, and
Cloud Code and Chrome
keep asking for more.
And so that's a little bit more
like this capability bound case.
And so I bring
that up just to say
that these are two distinct
engineering constraints that
emerge in different parts
of computer systems.
And so I think it's foolish
to think that one of these
is going to be the
only one that matters,
despite what some of the
proprietary lab people, I think,
say.
So the proprietary models do
dominate this capability bound
regime.
We'll talk about it.
Many people want to
maybe join those labs
and work on inference there.
But actually, I would say fine
tunes of open source models
are catching up here,
where maybe the frontier
capabilities are satisfactory
but not as much as you'd like.
And then you RL something
like DeepSeek V4,
and all of a sudden you
have better capabilities
and maybe you even
improve the efficiency.
And so this only in
the last, I would say,
three or six months has
that started to actually
really come true as open
models have caught up
and as more tasks have--
as intelligence has
increased in general.
So when capabilities
are satisfactory,
cost is going to be
your primary driver.
This efficiency bound regime--
model quality is easy.
And so the thing that you're
trying to achieve and engineer
in the system is
cost performance,
which is high
performance for low cost
or adequate performance
for the lowest cost maybe.
So many like right
now-- what this
looks like is these are
typically single GPU per replica
deployments.
The models that
are pretty good are
on the order of
billion parameters,
10 billion parameters,
50 billion parameters
fits inside the VRAM of
popular accelerators.
You switch over to multiple
GPUs if you have a low latency
budget.
Multiple GPUs allow you to split
work across multiple memory
pipes, and that allows you
to remove some bottlenecks
on latency.
But that is less
commonly the case
because these workloads
are, at this point,
often data processors,
subagents of background agents,
and rarely that chatbot
plus kind of workload,
where this human interactive
latency is really critical.
And so it's not
as often that you
have that super
tight latency budget.
So maybe an exception
to this is voice agents,
where people
yapping on the phone
don't need to talk
to superintelligence.
And they really want an
answer in 100 milliseconds.
And so that's maybe
a case where we're
starting to see some
of this multiple GPU
for an efficiency bound case.
The speaking of
voice models, these
are often multimodal
input structured output.
This is a case where the adding
additional modes gives you
access to more
information to the model.
But it's like a hit
on capabilities.
If you want the absolute
highest intelligence.
Right now, people get that
with language-only models.
At least the open source models.
And then the goal
is often to extract
some kind of structured
output from this,
so to turn unstructured
information
into structured information.
And this is something where you
don't need a IOI medal winning
intelligence to do this.
So good news about
this one is there's
many options for
your models here--
Quinn, Nemo Tron, GPT OSS
Gemma, Step from Stepfun,
Mistral, all of these.
And not only is there
this list of options here.
They are also-- each of
these is a model family.
So they have
different data mixes.
So maybe they're
optimized for coding.
Maybe they're
optimized for text.
They have different sizes.
They handle
different modalities.
So this is at the point where
you're spoiled for choice,
it feels like, in many cases.
On the other side when
capabilities are the bottleneck,
model quality is
really hard to hit.
The solution to that is make
the model really, really big.
We have only scaling as our
solutions to high intelligence
right now.
And so that has a
couple of consequences.
One is these are basically
always multiple GPUs
per replica.
Nobody can get enough HBM
to run a trillion parameter
MOE in a single chip.
And maybe I shouldn't
say that so much--
I forget how much HBM
there is in Cerebras,
but it's a big chip.
And then not only multiple
GPUs per replica but also
multiple nodes, so
multiple operating systems
possibly on distinct machines
talking to each other.
That comes up more often if you
have a relatively high latency
budget.
So like the tighter your
latency budget, the more
you want to keep the compute
and storage all really
nice and close to each other.
For capability bound stuff,
it's often the chatbot plus-- so
your ChatGPT, your Claude, or
the orchestrator of a background
agent.
I think I brushed over
this a little bit.
When I say subagent
of background agent,
a user types a prompt, and then
a whole cavalcade of things
occurs on the back
end in something
like a PR producing or code
review agent or whatever.
So these are often orchestrated
as multi-agent systems, which
have access to different
skills, different permissions,
boundaries, whatever.
At the top, there's often
an orchestrator agent
that's in charge of everything.
And that one is
where you generally
want the highest capabilities.
And then the things below can
often be faster, less capable
models solving similar tasks.
The similarity of this
to human organizations
I will leave as an
exercise for the reader.
These are often very tool
call heavy because what
uses intelligence if
it's not interacting
with the world-- compare
Mycroft Holmes and Sherlock.
And so they often
interact with the world.
And not only do they-- and I
mean interact with the world.
They don't just fire
off, do this thing.
They do the thing.
They observe the results
and interact with it.
So that has
implications for prefix.
Prefix hit rates, very high.
Prefix hit rates, very useful.
It also has implications
for latency.
It means that the latency
of these tool calls
is going to be an important
component of the operation
of your system.
The tool calls will range
in latency from milliseconds
to hours.
And so you need to
think about that.
In my experience, people
building these applications
often start with
a proprietary API.
They develop the
application there,
and then they want to
take additional control
over the inference.
There are fewer options
when that time comes.
I would say DeepSeek,
Kimmy GLM minimax,
and that's basically the
largest and most recent release
from each of them--
or in fact, maybe,
whichever one has most
recently released a model.
So that's your option.
I think once you start
doing fine tuning,
you get a little
bit more constrained
in being able to switch models
because the training software is
not super portable yet,
unlike the engines,
which we'll get to in a second.
Useful tool for mapping
out this space that I
like artificial analysis--
this is like a vibe check
or keeping up with the field
as it moves really quickly.
They give you these
nice charts with things
like their intelligence
index, which obviously hard
to define intelligence.
They give a number.
It's correlated with
my vibe judgment,
so I trust it as a measure
of my vibe judgment.
And so you have that.
This chart is one I come
back to quite a bit.
You have that on the y-axis
and on the x-axis price
to serve in dollars
per mega token.
This number is based off of
proprietary inference providers.
In my experience, beating this
is hard but not impossible.
And yeah, matching it also
already medium hard but far
from impossible, so long
as you have sufficient load
to fill up your hardware.
So we'll talk about the
performance optimization stuff
and why that is easier now than
it was like a year or two ago.
Actually, one of
the key components
for why this is easier is
because of the existence
of extremely high-quality
open source inference engines.
So what is an inference
engine really?
It's got a couple of components.
There's a server
task or process that
communicates with the
outside world that
generally controls some
tokenization and detokenization
work.
Tokenization is generally
really CPU intensive.
And so often done in
multiple processes.
We're in Python world here.
And detokenization,
you are mostly
tokenizing tokens
you've generated,
so they come a little
bit less quickly.
And so that's why I think you
can have multiple detokenizer
processes, but the
typical setup has one
or far fewer than tokenizers.
In between these is the
scheduler process on the CPU
that orchestrates all
the work on the GPU.
So all of the components
are really important,
but the bottleneck and key
that you want to think about
is the scheduler
process that defines
and schedules work on the GPUs.
GPU is a coprocessor.
You are giving it work
to do, and it gives you
the answers back later.
You want to make sure
that there is always
work for that thing to do.
And that is like-- that's
the DAO of PyTorch--
why PyTorch eager mode works
is that while the GPU is doing
a petaflop, Python is
taking its sweet time
of a second to decide
which kernel to run next.
And that's fine,
as long as you know
which kernel to run next
before the GPU finishes.
So this is the core piece here.
And what has emerged is the
common interchange or narrow
waist in between what
happens on the CPU
and what happens on the GPU
is PyTorch for the engines.
So there are a couple
of major options--
what people are using, like
open source options that are out
there, TensorRT LLM from NVIDIA
built on the TensorRT Runtime.
That's still your best
option for small models
and small batch
sizes of small models
but not your first choice.
vLLM has the widest
adoption I would say.
They were first to market
as a proper open source,
open governance project.
They have a bit of an
enterprise flavor at this point,
based off of the
development and the support
that they've received.
And then a slightly newer
entrant but still fairly mature
is SGLang.
They have a strong got
to go fast feel to them,
and they have a little bit
more of a startupy adoption
and support set.
So this slide just talks that
out a little bit in detail.
With TRT-LLM, it's a
compiled C++ runtime.
So all the stuff I was showing
you is basically in C++,
especially once it's
out and deployed.
So that avoids the problem
of bottlenecking on the CPU
without having to be a smart
engineer because the code is
just faster or being a different
kind of smart engineer.
No hate to my C++ friends.
NVIDIA is the sole
developer of this.
They still release some of
their new exciting projects
and techniques
there, but there's
a bit-- it feels like a slightly
decreased investment in TRT-LLM
over time in favor of them
supporting these open libraries.
And I think that's a
general thing NVIDIA does.
They build the software and
demonstrate to other people
how to use their hardware.
And then somebody
else comes along,
and they go back to
making their money off
of selling those chips.
But again, still some benefits.
VLLM, the big
thing here, this is
like a proper open governance,
like Linux Foundation umbrella
project, like
Postgres or PyTorch.
And that has implications for
the manner in which you join it
and what you might
expect the future of it,
how it might develop.
SGLang on the other hand,
right now, it's open source
but closed governance.
There's a specific
nonprofit that
owns this on behalf
of the maintainers
or composed of the maintainers.
So that's like maybe--
struggling to think
of a good closed
governance, open source
project that doesn't
have a big company behind it.
And they have spun out this
startup to develop many--
the founding team.
Anyway, so we'll see how
these two things develop.
I'll say vLLM and SGLang--
I'd say SGLang has this very
more extremely performance
focused engineering culture.
There's 50 bajillion
different versions of SGLang,
as Docker images, as
branches or whatever,
and they each have tiny
little optimizations in them.
Whereas the LLM gets things
into main a little bit more.
And so there's less of
that absurd hackery.
This is my experience
working with them.
So yeah, I haven't
found a strong reason
to prefer one or the other yet.
They both do great work.
And as people who mostly
consume these kinds of engines,
it's nice to have more suitors.
You're going to be serving--
you don't necessarily
want to write your
own engine, but you
do want to get to know them.
There's a nice
project mini and nano
vLLM that have simple
implementations of engines.
Help you learn the architecture.
Alexa Gaudich did a great
walkthrough of vLLM.
And if you check out the slides.
I put them on a
notebook on Modal
so you can run them
on multiple GPUs
and see how disaggregated
prefilled decode works
in a notebook.
Another useful resource, I
really Deep Wiki from Cognition.
It's a bunch of indexed
software repositories
that you can ask questions.
It's nice because you don't
have to have the code downloaded
in the place where an agent is
running where you're typing.
You can just look
it up on your phone
and just be like,
hey, wait a second.
How does the radix cache in
SGLang support hybrid models?
I think it doesn't, but
Deep Wiki would tell you.
And it's got diagrams.
It's organized.
It's queryable.
It's more than just
having the code,
but then it's always really
nice to also have the code
and explore it with an agent.
Use your own thinking
tokens, not just
the ones you're paying for.
OK.
So models and engines--
so you've got your model.
You've got your engine.
Where are you going to run this?
This has been a specter
that has been haunting us,
the Specter of what does
this hardware look like.
One thing I will say
is it feels like there
are two workloads here from
the hardware perspective.
You have the prefill
part and the decode part.
So in prefill, you have some
large number of input tokens.
Here there's only four.
But usually, these days in
almost all the workloads
we're talking about
here, it's hundreds,
thousands, tens of thousands,
hundreds of thousands.
And so that comes in.
And in order to
process them, you're
going to move many
gigabytes of weights
out of the memory
of your accelerator
into registers to
calculate something.
And then you have to move
all the weights in order
to calculate that or all
the active parameters.
And then once you then
move over to-- that's
the prefill or the prompt
processing or the input phase.
During output phase, every
time you create a token,
you also need to take all
the weights out of memory,
put them into registers, and
do a calculation with them.
And per rough rule of thumb, per
batch element-- so per token,
per request, you're probably
going to do on the order of two
or three floating
point operations.
Multiply with something
and accumulate it
into something else.
So why does this matter?
So that suggests that
in the decode phase
we're doing a few
operations per byte loaded.
And the bad news is that the
trend of hardware, like in GPUs
and elsewhere, is for increasing
ridge point arithmetic
intensity.
The point at which you are
using all of the arithmetic
bandwidth that you
have, and that's
the limit on your performance.
And because the memory bandwidth
is generally so much lower,
you end up slowed.
You aren't able to achieve
that actual full arithmetic
bandwidth.
So some representative
numbers down here
for the tensor
cores of a variety
of different recent NVIDIA GPUs.
They're in the hundreds--
maybe a thousand
operations per byte.
And during decode, you're
maybe doing a couple
of operations per byte.
And so you are going
to struggle to make
full use of the accelerator.
It's costing you the same
amount during that time.
So you're going to end up
thinking about optimizing those
separately from one another.
That's why they
already showed up
in the definition of our
applications and our workloads.
In order to do this well,
I think the only option
these days, in my
experience, is recent data
center and Tensor
Core SXM NVIDIA GPUs.
So these are marketing terms, so
let me break that down for you.
Data centers-- what
NVIDIA uses to talk
about the interconnect
housing, et cetera of the GPUs.
So we see in the top right--
I believe that's a
H100 SXM machine.
Yeah, but it might be a B20.
But the point is
a couple of things
you can notice here-- it's a
little hard to see on the slide,
so let me go back here.
The little blue
blocks there, that's
the high bandwidth memory.
This is on substrate
but off chip memory.
It's like soldered in place.
It's not like the RAM you have
at home that you can plug-in
and out.
And that ultra low latency
and ultra high bandwidth
are really critical for the
decode phase, especially.
So you really want that.
And that's one reason why--
and not like GDDR
memory-based NVIDIA GPUs.
This also is going to
give you higher capacity
in memory in general.
I think that's just an artifact
of how these things have
been deployed.
I don't think it's impossible
to build a chip with a giant GER
RAM stack.
I just don't think that
NVIDIA offers that.
But let me know if I'm wrong.
SXM is the mounting form factor.
This is replacing PCIe, the
little finger like toothbrush
thing at the bottom of a GPU,
the GPUs you've probably seen.
You can see the connector
there at the arrow.
So this allows for
better power delivery.
And so this is where you'll
get the full wattage of GPUs.
Where do these limitations on
memory bandwidth and arithmetic
bandwidth come from?
Fundamentally, they
come from the power
that's delivered to the
chip and the ability
to egress the heat
that it produces.
And SXM, this mounting
factor, gives better power
delivery and better
installation in data centers,
and so the fastest chips will
have this somewhere in their SKU
name.
And then finally, yeah,
NVLink and InfiniBand
for connecting GPUs and
connecting nodes to each other.
I'm not going to talk too
much about that today.
Then Tensor Core-- this will
show up in the names of GPUs
as well.
Tensor Cores are essentially a
matmul ASIC inside of the GPU
that NVIDIA stapled on
after Google made the TPU.
That's going to start
a bunch of fights.
But let's say this is
essentially a distinct hardware
unit programmed distinctly
from the rest of the GPU.
And it is where 99%
of the FLOPs are
in your contemporary hardware.
And it is only able to do
matrix-matrix multiplication.
So hot tip-- if you're thinking
about weird model architectures,
make sure that they can take
advantage of matrix matrix
multiplication.
Don't make the
transformers mistake
of having your
inference look like
matrix-vector multiplication.
Quick, shameless
plug here for if you
want an intro to a lot of
the terms that I just used.
Wrote this GPU glossary.
Collects everything
from warp schedulers up
to compiler flags in one place.
Also a bunch of stuff on
performance optimization,
like that ridge point diagram.
So that's book knowledge.
If you want a little bit
more street knowledge,
tensara.org that a
friend of mine made,
it's a leak cheat code
for GPU programming.
And yeah, I guess
it's a shameless plug
because it runs on Moodle.
OK.
So I jumped right into
talking about GPUs
without talking about what
your other options are.
I think right now CPUs generally
can't achieve acceptable latency
for the models that
people want to run.
You really need
HBM, so that makes
it hard to use most CPUs because
they're deployed with RAM
and processor distinct.
These things do exist.
There were some troubles with
Intel's HBM being able to feed--
the HBM and the CPU being able
to keep pace with each other.
One big problem here is that
GPUs give the programmer control
of the L1 cache
SM shared memory,
and that's really
important for being
able to make use of very
high arithmetic bandwidth.
And yeah, so people
are doing a lot
of really excellent
work on this,
so I'd expect this
to change over time.
And models will get smaller.
Models get smaller.
CPUs get bigger.
This will cross
over, and there will
be a lot of really
awesome CPU inference
happening but not today.
AMD GPUs-- I don't use--
I haven't used them very much.
I've heard the programming on
them is somewhat challenging,
and achieving the full-rated
performance is challenging,
but they've also been doing
a lot of excellent work,
so watch that space.
TPUs-- I personally
am a little spooked
by the idea of having only
one supplier end to end.
You can buy corals--
little tiny like TPUs.
But I have a 2070 that I put
under my pillow at night.
And I feel like I
know that machine.
And like a TPU, I don't.
And then there's the more
seriously economic concerns
of purchasing from such a
tightly integrated monopoly as
opposed to a loosely integrated
monopoly with NVIDIA.
There are other inference
chips on the horizon.
They're generally harder-- they
have the same single supplier
program in general.
Many of them have walked back.
They're like, oh, buy
a chip and install it
in your own racks thing.
And they generally don't
deploy via the hyperscalers.
And the cloud experience
of programming
them is like with TPUs.
They built it.
Then you use it via their cloud.
That's allowing them to move
faster, so no shade on that.
But this also makes them harder
to program lower installed base.
There are not like 13-year-old
basement dweller hackers reverse
engineering the instruction set,
like there is with NVIDIA GPUs.
So you don't have that breadth.
So that makes me a little
bit concerned about them,
but it's also very clear that
there's a lot going on there.
All right.
So that's hardware.
So we don't just need hardware.
We need to plug it in to things
like power and networking
and get things running on it.
Your deployment
options are basically
constrained by the hardware.
So GPUs and HBM are scarce.
They're likely to remain scarce.
And so because of
that, inference
is mostly served
right now, not local.
Most inference applications
you're going to build right now
are going to run in a data
center on behalf of clients.
I do expect that to change--
another watch this space
compared to databases.
How many SQLite databases
do you think there
are versus Postgres databases?
There's trillions
of SQLite databases.
Somebody calculated it.
So eventually, things will go
out to the edge substantially.
But for now, cloud deployment--
ultra low latency budgets are
generally eaten into by network.
So you're losing on the
order of tens of milliseconds
if you have regional deployments
or hundreds of milliseconds
if you have global deployments.
So that increases the
pressure on latency
and pushes you to these
more complex regional
or edge in the data
center sense deployments.
And then because these things
are scarce and in demand,
they're expensive.
And so you're going
to be focusing
a lot on maximizing what you're
getting out of the hardware.
This has maybe been-- this is
like the implicit driver behind
how much we've been concerned
about performance in this entire
discussion--
the cost of an employee to have
an 8x B200 machine running.
So people care
about performance.
Another problem--
GPUs fail a lot.
So mean time to failure,
NVIDIA H100s measured
in weeks or days, not years.
So if you read war stories
from older engineers
about working with spinning
disks, it's more like that.
You have to build in an
assumption of failure
and therefore like redundancy,
so that faults in hardware
don't become failures
in your system.
The good news is
if you're building
an inference system your
life is a little bit easier.
Training requires basically
all GPUs to be up at all times,
or else the whole world stops
because all the replicas
are independent.
You just route to a different
replica and keep going.
But it is a concern about
robustness, reliability,
and cost performance.
So we wrote a little bit
about what we've observed.
I'm not going to go in great
detail, but check out this blog
if you want to learn a little
bit about what this looks
like when you're
looking at thousands
or low tens of
thousands of GPUs.
You could see different
cloud providers have
very different failure
rates-- for instance,
different deployments.
Some are better than others.
And there are things you
can do to work on this.
But the bigger challenge
with inference serving
is variability in traffic.
So this is simulated.
But what we typically see
with inference applications
on our platform is that
over a period of time
the request per
minute is variable.
There's seasonal
variability, but there's also
very big swings in demand.
I think this is partly
due the fastest growing
companies in history are
being created right now.
We have social media to
distribute products really
quickly.
And so there's a number of
dynamics that lead to this.
And with inference as
opposed to training,
you don't like engineer and
plan around these things.
They just happen to you.
So key thing that
we work on at Modal
is trying to allow you to
provision only the GPUs
that you want or that you
need at any given time.
The default thing would
be to just buy them.
Maybe rack them ahead of time.
And then you have to guess
how big your peak is going
to be, and then
anytime off peak,
you're still paying
for the hardware,
whether that's directly in
the form of cloud rental
or indirectly as
amortized costs.
So this is madly inefficient.
If you look online
or in this blog post,
people report like 30%,
40% utilization here.
So these are made
up numbers, but they
are tended to be true to life.
So solution-- OK.
Well, let me just get
GPUs as I need them.
The problem is that
it's really hard
to make the startup of new
replicas of inference servers
really fast.
And so if you don't engineer
this part of your system
carefully, you can have poor
utilization and poor quality
of service.
You both have GPUs
you're not using
that have stuck around
after you spin them up,
and you will miss peaks.
So the goal is to achieve
fast and automatic allocation
so that you can have
maximal utilization
and good quality of service.
So for interest of time, I
won't go through this in detail.
There's an extremely detailed
blog post about this, about some
of the approaches
that we took-- talking
about the actual internals and
hopes that other folks can learn
from them.
So the basic idea
is, number one,
don't spin up a
machine from scratch
just because a user
request came in.
Operate a buffer
of idle machines
ready to go to handle new
traffic as things change.
So have a couple spare.
This is particularly
important if you
have multiple applications
scaling up on the same pool.
So if you're running multiple
different deployments,
you might not know which one is
going to need to scale up next.
So this one-- we're massively
a multi-tenant system,
so this is one we
think about a lot.
Check out the blog
post for details
on the way we solve this with
classic operations, research,
linear solver approach,
managing the size of that buffer
and taking into account price.
So that one is really important
for multi-tenant systems,
especially--
But for all systems, if
you're creating and destroying
replicas, you're probably using
something like a container, VM.
You need to get the files that
are necessary for that thing
to run onto the system
from somewhere--
somewhere in cloud storage.
Our solution is, one, get
the loading of the whole file
system out of the way
of container start.
So lazily load the
file system, but then
also eagerly load
the first things
that are going to be needed--
PyTorch, Python Core
operating system libraries.
Fetch those things concurrently
with the container replica
starting, and then store those
in a multi-tier cloud cache.
Everything from the Linux
page cache on a replica,
all the way up to blob storage
with all kinds of things
in between that can
deliver that faster.
Again, the full version here
is important for a wide variety
of inference workloads or
a multi-tenant environment,
but these same
basic technologies
are what you're
likely to use even
in a single tenant deployment
or even a single workload.
Then you want to
start the application.
And this takes minutes for
things like SGLang and VLM.
They do just in
time compilation.
They do CUDA graph capture.
They do Torch compilation.
All of these things
take time, and it
seems like this is something
that you just have to wait for.
But every process is actually
just a data structure
in the end.
So this is a representation of
a Linux process, representation
of some part of what might
be on the GPU at the bottom.
This is, in the end, just data.
There's some exceptions
with things like TCP sockets
that require some surgery, but
fundamentally, this is data.
You create it.
If you how to
create it, store it,
and then you can restore
it from storage faster
than you can recreate it.
So you have checkpoint
restore technologies,
like CRIU and CUDA
checkpoint to use here.
NVIDIA also released
a blog post yesterday
about their system for
this GPU memory service
and others as part of
upcoming Dynamo releases,
So, check out this blog post
and that one for details.
So this allows you to operate
a much more efficient inference
deployment.
All right.
So we've got the thing deployed.
And now, how do we
know if it's broken,
and how do we fix it when it is?
So classes of bugs that
you're going to see--
you've got application level
bugs, model quality bugs,
and performance bugs,
or failures to hit, SLO.
So application-level bugs, these
are a shared responsibility
between you and the application
developers and stakeholders.
So these are very tricky.
And as somebody who's mostly
working on the infra side,
I get to avoid
thinking about them.
For my own applications, The,
things that I run myself,
they are-- yeah--
some of the trickier ones.
They cross machine
learning and correctness
stuff, user experience things.
Yeah.
So the things that you have a
little bit more control over
or responsibility
for as an inference
engineer-- model quality bugs.
The model looks good at the
point that you deploy it,
and then it starts behaving
badly in production.
That could just be
because the things
are different in production.
So what academics
would call train test
skew or train serve skew,
but maybe the most common one
in my experience
is tokenizer bugs.
Tokens, as I think Albert
pointed out in his talk-- tokens
are cursed.
Tokens are bad.
We wish we didn't have them, but
we have them at least for now.
And tokenizers
have, if anything,
gotten-- tokenizers
and chat templates.
I'm merging these two together,
but you take a string.
You augment the user input
string or the harnesses input
string with special
strings or special tokens.
Those things have only increased
in complexity over time.
When open source models
are first released,
these are almost
assuredly buggy.
And then these are slowly
beaten down over time.
So that's actually-- if
you're looking for open source
like contributions, if
you can run the models
and discover these
tokenizer bugs,
this is something you can
both report and ideally fix
in the engines or in
the model definitions.
It's valuable open
source contribution
work with many eyes.
All bugs are shallow,
even tokenizer bugs.
Yeah.
So performance bugs, you'll see.
Yeah, regressions over
time, and then surprising
cross replica
differences, especially
in a heterogeneous
computing environment.
I use the term observability
in describing this-- the way
to think about debugging.
Observability
fundamentally means can you
debug just from the logs.
Charity majors describes this
as saying that observability
is dual to steerability
or controllability,
and this comes from linear
systems analysis for the EE
people in the room.
So the idea is,
can you just look
at what you've logged
about the application,
figure out what was wrong with
it, fix the code and ship?
Obviously you would also
run tests and stuff,
but this is a vision.
It's a dream-- without having
to come up with a minimal repro
or whatever.
Some other way to
take a complex--
likely distributed
system and debug it.
So at the application
level, this generally
has to be bespoke.
You can roll your own
with OpenTelemetry based
tooling in Datadog or whatever.
The same things
you use in general
often work pretty well here,
but at the application level,
things are a little weirder.
They're fuzzier.
They're more
machine-learning like,
and there are specialized tools
for this, like Lang, Smith
and Braintrust.
I don't have a ton of
experience at this level,
but I've heard good
things about using those
and about rolling their
own, so dealer's choice.
For model quality,
obviously, you
want to make sure you've
measured model quality ahead
of time, so you have a
baseline to compare to.
So running evaluations
before deployment, but then
yeah, just aggressive logging
of traces and user feedback.
For tokenizers, I am
begging you log token IDs
as part of your logging.
Don't just log the strings.
You will have trouble recreating
those token IDs later.
And this is bugs that are very
subtle expressed in Unicode
are very obvious--
expressed in token IDs.
Where did that number come from?
So log that.
Performance-- again, log
more metrics than you need.
The more stuff you
put, the more likely
it is that you have logged
the one smoking gun that
points to the actual problem.
So I think of it as log the
initial object in all things
you might want to log, and then
you'll filter down from there.
Yeah.
On evals-- just
a side note here,
more at the application level.
This is how you
build observability
for all maps at the high-level.
Evals in many ways they are like
tests in that they're thankless.
They're annoying to write.
They cramp your style.
They're difficult and
time consuming to produce.
It's low status
labor, but they're
critical to developing a
successful application.
And so you can start
with something as simple
as a Jupyter Notebook
or an Excel spreadsheet
with some prompts
or whatever in it.
And that will already
deliver some value
before you build
the whole system.
And it is useful for debugging
deployments and knowing
what kind of performance
you should expect,
but it's also something you--
if you make the model agnostic,
you can use them to derive those
more application and product
level decisions.
Which model should we use?
Or what should we run it on?
How much can we
quantize this model?
Fundamentally, models
and deployments
have turned out to
be pretty temporary.
They're swapped in and out.
Evals are forever.
In some sense, they always
last longer than models
because they have to at least
last long enough to compare
one model to another.
So yeah, use them for--
and then you can also
use them for QA with all
the other things you're
going to be doing to improve
your inference deployment,
whether that's fine
tuning, distillation,
benchmarking, like unhinged
lossy optimizations,
or speculative models.
More on that in a second.
Quick set of metrics to log--
rough and ready.
The things we already
mentioned-- time to first token,
time per output token,
or inter token latency,
time to last token, request per
second, or queries per second.
So requests per second is
more at the user level.
Queries per second is more
at the language model level.
Anyway, you definitely define
those two terms separately
and think at the level of the
user or outside of the system
and then within the system
when you have things
like tool calls returning.
Queuing-- in general,
many of these systems
from the GPU and its SMs, all
the way up to your Kubernetes,
like your ingress or whatever.
There will be queues, and they
will be a major contributor
to your tail latencies.
So when you want to debug while
your time to first token or time
to last token is going way up.
It's probably there's
a queue somewhere.
Then you want to these split in
the workload prefill and decode.
You want to when those things
are running and what volume--
cached, prefill.
How often are we actually seeing
a prefix that we'd seen before?
If you really want
to get more advanced,
log all your prefixes
forever, and then offline
run-- what would be
the optimal prefix
hit rate if I had an
infinitely sized cache
and perfect detection to
compare those numbers to.
It's nice to have a goal
you can never reach.
It gives you something to do
for the rest of your life.
Then you want these metrics
at a per replica level,
and then you want them
at an aggregate level
because they're
generally sensible at--
aggregates give you a sense
for the overall distribution,
and they allow you
to compare replicas
to the current state of
things, not just things
you've measured offline.
And then you want to measure
these in median and in tail
and as averages.
Averages help you compute things
like throughputs and right
sizing.
And the meat and the
quantiles give you
a sense for user experience.
And as I showed with the
little demo of the token timing
simulator, those tail
latencies, despite them
looking like small
numbers, like 5%,
they're really most of the time.
And then lastly on the
hardware level-- temperature,
power-- these things matter.
Not every deployment
gets these right.
There are problems.
There's bad cooling.
You want to watch this.
And then utilization of things,
like the memory capacity
and the kernels.
Sorry-- the utilization of CUDA
streams, kernel utilization.
How often is work
running on the GPU?
These are the things that you
can measure really easily,
asynchronously with
low or no overhead.
The other things you might
want to measure generally
have additional overhead,
at least for now.
And so you can't get the lowest
level performance counters
without taking a
performance hit.
That's generally unacceptable.
So this is a little dashboard
for this on an internal alpha
that we've built at modal
for tracking these things.
This is a recent fun deployment
I had of a multi-modal model.
You can see there's lots of
spikes in the P95 and P99,
even though the
P50s look very fine.
And then you can see a couple of
things that jump out from this.
It's the inter token
latencies are correlated
in time with queuing, so that
suggests that the latencies that
are very long are actually
a request it was generating
tokens, and then
it got kicked out
so something else
could generate tokens,
and it got cycled back in.
This is a behavior
inference engines will
do to try to achieve fair
distribution of token throughput
to requests.
And that's bad.
That maybe means I have
too many requests going
to the individual replicas
here, and I need to lower that.
Or it could be that there's
something slowing down
in the replicas.
I didn't fully debug this
because the performance
was acceptable for the
domain, which was an art show.
Yeah.
All right.
So speaking of optimizing
performance, how do you do this?
Not just like looking
at those charts there,
but then how do you fix the
problems that you observe?
So with performance
optimization, I think,
yeah, the same lessons that
are elsewhere really apply.
There are big things
that you can work on,
and the biggest things
are speculative decoding
and quantization.
These are generally--
their low hanging fruit,
but they often are
application specific.
And that means
that you can't just
stand on the shoulders of
giants like you can elsewhere.
Then there's the grind
of medium benefit tasks
that involve engineering on
the host rather than the GPU,
and then only after
that should you
start thinking about
doing GPU side work
and doing things like kernel
optimization, where you'll
get a few percentage points
speedups, which really matters
at very large scale but
only once you've gotten
the big things out of the way.
So let's talk about these
in a little bit more detail.
So apologies-- this was a light
mode diagram that I copy pasted.
So speculative decoding--
tries to solve this problem
where decode has too
few operations per byte.
And the solution-- and if you're
more of an algorithms person,
it's that you have one or a
small number of query vectors
in your attention.
And yeah, and one token
in your MLPs or MOE.
And so the solution
then is, all right--
so we aren't using
all the flops,
but we are using all
the memory bandwidth.
What if we gave those extra
flops something to do,
even if it wasn't
always useful work?
So what if we guessed
what the next things
to come after Modal is a
serverless computing company?
We guess that.
We put it in, and we run on
those speculated or drafted
tokens.
And we run the full
model, the model
we want to get
tokens from on that.
And then we run a
Metropolis-Hastings style
rejection sampling
algorithm that
guarantees the tokens
that we get out
have the exact same
probability distribution
as the tokens that went in.
For greedy decoding, that
just means take all the tokens
that agree in a prefix.
So if you have
temperature equals 0,
it's just take
serverless computing.
And then the first
token that's different,
use one from the target model.
So when you are at--
when you are memory
bound, which is generally
going to start to
show up when you have
very tight latency budgets and
smaller models on big GPUs,
this becomes like an absolute
no brainer to implement.
And the reason why I say
speculation is all you need
is because it gives you these
very large, integral measured
speed up factors.
People talk about
speedups of 2x, 4x, 8x.
And it is also, as
my colleague David
Wang put it, crazy bitter
lesson pilled, which
is to say to create those draft
tokens, you need another model.
And that model
needs to be trained,
and it will get better with
more data and more compute,
just like the base models do.
And so using application
specific data,
you can increase your speed
up from speculative decoding
from a factor of 2 to
a factor of 6, which
is a factor of 3 speed up.
That's very big.
It's the difference between does
this application work or not.
And so we're very big believers.
This math here, this is the
simplest mathematical model
of speculative
decoding that gives you
this exponential speed up from
increased acceptance lengths.
We do observe things
like this in production.
Detailed mathematical models
have things diminishing returns
or whatever, but you do observe
very substantial speed ups
from custom speculators.
And this in addition
to the release
of things like SGLang and BLM
and their excellent engineering
work on those, the creation of
really good speculative models
is one of the other
reasons why people
can run their own
inference now in a way
that they couldn't
a year or two ago.
So there are many
approaches to speculation.
Simple one is n-gram,
a language model
you might learn about in a
math class or a stats class.
Just repeat sequences of tokens
that appeared in the prompt.
If you see n minus
1 tokens, guess
the next token is the n-th.
That works OK, but
nowadays, many models
are released with multi-token
prediction built in,
so the last heads of
the model don't just
produce a single token.
They produce several.
This has benefits at train time
and at inference time, which
is really nice.
Usually these are two groups of
engineers who hate each other.
But yeah, so this is
becoming almost standard.
It's generally
released with things.
Though it's a little
tricky sometimes to train
multi-token prediction.
And you can do a little bit
better at inference time.
What people have
found is that if you
train your draft model
based off of the hidden
states of the model, even
the earlier hidden states.
Interesting phenomenon
in these models
is like with depth, they
become more specialized to just
predicting the next token.
Over time, they're doing
interesting combinations
of reasoning across tokens.
They maybe don't know what
the next token is going to be.
The know the next idea or
the next couple of ideas,
and that sharpens over
time as you go deeper.
Look at some of the model
surgery papers for stuff
about that-- layer skipping.
So you actually want the
earlier layers in there.
And that's tricky
to do with MTP,
but it's easy to do offline.
Eagle is one of the first
things that did this.
So you train this thing
alongside the model.
And then D flash is
the one that we've
gotten excited about at Modal.
It's like Eagle, but it's like
a denoising diffusion language
model.
And diffusion language
models have generally
struggled to reach the
highest capabilities,
but diffusion is generally
a better fit for hardware.
It has a higher
arithmetic intensity--
naturally maps better.
You don't have that
prefilled decode split.
So I'm really
excited about that.
And so we're big
in on that and have
been working on things like
improvements with the authors
and on getting it well
integrated into SGLang.
So that's speculation.
Quantization-- that is your
other biggest lever to pull.
If you can go from FP8 to FP4,
that's like a 2x speed up.
And that's a 2x speed up
both for memory bound things
and for compute bound things.
So for memory bound
things, you're
cutting the memory
bandwidth demand in half
because there's fewer bytes.
And Tensor Cores and
other floating point math,
they are quoted in
an ops per second,
and that ops per second scales
linearly with the bytes.
So really, there's bytes
of operations per second
that they actually
have as bandwidth.
So the same thing
basically applies.
So this unfortunately requires
full stack coordination
for a couple of reasons.
One is that if you want to
operate with FP4 with hardware
acceleration, you need Blackwell
GPUs in the NVIDIA stack.
So like this-- and
on the other hand,
quantization changes
model behavior.
So you have to think about this
at the application layer, right?
And so you can't just--
the evals, or vibe
checks, or testing
in prod-- that is the handoff
between the application
layer and the hardware layer.
You need to make sure that
that's good enough that you can
confidently ship this change.
A couple things about the
model behavior changes.
Generally, it's worse
on longer sequences.
You have lower precision.
With longer sequences, you
have more accumulation.
So there's more
accumulated error.
And so whether it's
in or out sequences,
you're going to
struggle more here.
But that means with
shorter sequences,
you can do this with
more confidence.
FP8 is pretty standard.
It's supported on
hopper and above.
FP4 is relatively cutting edge.
This is generally done in
only the MLP or MOE layers,
and not in the attention layers.
Attention involves a
lot more accumulation,
and so it's a
little bit trickier.
And so yeah, but matmuls are
generally the bottleneck or more
frequently the bottleneck.
And so you still see the
roughly linear speed up.
You might want to do
things like quantize
or compress the KV cache.
This is pretty hard.
It should generally be
done, I think, at train time
as the DeepSeek V4 model does.
Just like-- yeah, it is
trickier to get right
than weight quantization.
And for all these
things, this is very much
the current state of affairs.
And to my knowledge, I might
have missed recent papers.
OK.
So closing out here,
yeah, the next tier
is getting the CPU out
of the way of the GPU.
Don't block it.
So you're basically submitting
a bunch of work to the GPU.
Make sure that there's always
something for it to do.
Key technique for this
CUDA graph capture
turns many CUDA kernel
launches into one.
This is from a profiler showing
many CUDA graphs launched
at once.
So make sure to turn that one
on in your inference engine.
Key tool for looking
for host overhead
is GPU power draw or temperature
not being as high of a level.
So these are two
replicas, one of which
was running slower
than the other.
And the second replica
was only drawing
2 kilowatts instead of
the full three kilowatts
plus it should have
been able to draw.
And taking a look at that with
a tool like the Torch Profiler
that I think you saw in previous
lectures, or the Nsight systems
profiler, both of which are
built on the same CUDA profiling
tools interface from NVIDIA--
able to determine
that one of the causes
was that one of the workers
that was participating
in a collective was
struggling behind the others.
I haven't fully
actually debug this one.
This is a bit of a
live this week problem,
but suspect NUMA
Affinity problems.
And so NUMA Affinity
is a very hard thing
to know about, especially if
you have heterogeneous hardware.
But temperature or power
draw is very easy and free.
So watch this guy
and then dive in.
But you don't have
to go get that fancy.
You can literally just
use something like py-spy
to watch what's
going on the host
and look for bottlenecks
that you can optimize.
We have a blog post about how
we came up with a very simple,
like, Python-only solution to
speed up multimodal inference
in SGLanf by over 10% by just
like caching a pointer basically
in a Python dict, instead of
recreating it on every request--
every tensor on every request.
And that, yeah, no CUDA mode,
no Nsight profiler, just py-spy.
So only then is it time to
consider GPU optimization
kernels out there.
They're pretty good.
They're often very close
to the speed of light.
You have lots of people
trying to work on these,
and they're very
reusable in general.
So there's lots of good
libraries for these.
And that means there are
only percentage points
to gain in most cases.
So only get to it when
percentage points are
the thing that you care about.
The tool for that--
the primary tool
for that being Nsight compute,
which can help you measure
the lowest level hardware
utilization-- actually
measure things how much of the
arithmetic bandwidth and memory
bandwidth am I using and map
things about your performance
directly onto, say, the
assembler to look for pipeline
stalls or scoreboard stalls.
Yeah.
And just to point again
at before you go this--
before you pull the fancy
tools out, the way [INAUDIBLE]
writes fast kernels
is with a whiteboard.
So think about what
are the bottlenecks.
What are the most important
things to optimize?
What speed are they able
to achieve and reason
from there before pulling
out the empirical techniques.
So check out their blog
on that for details.
OK.
So I don't have much time.
And we were-- yeah.
I will stick around
for extra questions.
So I'll just say what's next--
lossy weird optimizations.
Skip layers, quantize
things, prune,
lossy speculative decoding, mega
kernels for speculative coding,
and draft models are
ready for specific layers
in the future for whole models.
I said NVIDIA GPUs
are your only option,
but that's very much
only true right now.
NVIDIA is already going to
be releasing a hybrid rack
in the next generation that
includes LPUs from Grok.
That actually to assert--
it doesn't actually
map onto the prefilled
decode split just yet,
but I think that is basically
an artifact of history.
And in the future,
prefill and decode
will be done by
distinct accelerators
if demand continues.
Great.
I promise this one
to people on Twitter,
so I will have to
go through this one.
What's next?
I talked about a
lot of this mostly
as though you'd be
writing the code yourself.
So for the future of a lot
of software engineering
is going to include agents--
LLM inference as part of the
actual software engineering.
In order to make this
work, you don't just
get to just prompt
and turn away.
Your job is now to build
the system that measures
the correctness of agents.
They will then do things like
benchmarking, configuration,
monitoring.
You need to what tools and
MCPs to connect them to,
what metrics they need.
It'll be a while before people
trust models with your AWS root
account to set up
monitoring or whatever.
So it's your job to
understand that and build it.
And I think we talked
about BLM, SGLang.
They're great
software, but they are
built on the assumption
that making that software
is really expensive.
And if you can write a
bespoke engine per deployment
very cheaply, then maybe
that's a better strategy.
So check VibeServe,
a recent paper
from the home lab for some
gestures in that direction.
So we're very
excited about this.
At Modal, we really like
engineering systems.
And we don't typing
things by hand
and building white glove
specific deployments for people.
We want this to be scalable.
And agents, I think, are going
to be part of that story.
All right.
Thank you.
[APPLAUSE]